so you'll undoubtedly you've noticed
that this is being taped so the tapes
will show up on some relatively regular
schedule I wouldn't expect that
precisely because I don't want to make
any promises about you know exactly how
quickly that'll be done
Martin Jang here is doing it on its own
accord so it's like you know two thumbs
up for Martin as far as I'm concerned so
because he's done this for a number of
my courses and it's a lot of work and
it's much appreciated so anyways that's
why all of this stuff is set up so I
think I told you pretty much about what
the class entails on your part you know
and if you you've heard this lecture and
I'm sure at least a reasonable number of
you have heard me lecture before so you
sort of know what how I'm going to
lecture and that was more or less how
I'm going to do it I'm hoping that you
know we can make this class like deadly
successful that's the idea and that
you'll regard it as something that no
depending on your participation
obviously you'll regard it as something
that's really valuable I'm telling you
the stuff I've learned that I'm telling
you about it has been so useful to me
that I can't buy I can't I can't really
even communicate how useful it's been
it's been unbelievably useful and you
know partly what I'm going to explain to
you if I can is why you know there are
tenets of classical morality and there's
a variety of them and one of them is for
example don't lie and you know that's a
tough one because you might think well
you know why not really why not I mean
if you can if if you can set up a
situation so that you benefit from from
an untruth what stops you from doing it
you know and Dostoevsky and one of his
most famous statements he said if
there's no God everything is permitted
and it's a take-off on Nietzschean
thinking too and it's a problem that he
thought would be the fundamental problem
of the 20th century and I think he was
absolutely right and it's a question
very much worth thinking about it's like
why bother with things that are moral
why do things right is there even such a
thing as doing things right these are
great questions you
and hopefully I'm what I'm going to try
to do with you guys is to show you what
the consequence I've been thinking about
those things for you know it's almost 30
years I guess now and I you know I've
got a ways certainly a ways that has
been satisfying to me and I want to tell
you what I've concluded and then you can
decide for yourself if you think it's
useful and one thing I would really like
encourage you to do is like you should
be skeptical about what I'm telling you
really like you should question it like
I don't mean the kind of skepticism
that's like this because like you know
I'm not here to prove myself to you at
all and you're not here to prove
yourself to me either so you have to
listen you have to attend but by the
same token I would say like I'm telling
you things that I've tried to hammer to
deth I've tried to see if they were
wrong you know because that's how you're
supposed to test ideas you throw out an
idea and you hammer the hell out of it
see if you can see if it's wrong not
whether it's right because that's
ideological thinking and the things I'm
telling you are things I could not
disprove they seem to stand up and I've
tried multiple tests you know so one of
them is sort of a Concilium stess t' and
the concilium says a word that was
defined by Edward or Wilson and what
when an explanation is Concilium what
that means is that it's coherent across
multiple levels of analysis you know and
so I've tried to test the ideas that I'm
describing to you I've tried to
determine whether they're logically
coherent and appropriate at the level of
general psychology and clinical
psychology and neuroscience and
narrative theory and religious thinking
and then also to see if they're actually
applicable as practical as practical
realities in day-to-day life and and in
social life and as far as I'm concerned
they stand up that's been my experience
and I've also watched people over many
years now try to apply them in their own
lives and all I've been able to see so
far with my graduate students and so on
is that they works so you know arrayed
for that and so we're going to try to
understand some basic issues like what
the utility
truth is and that's a really important
question it's a it's maybe the
fundamental question is truth useful and
if so how and why and like man we're
going to go after that especially with
regards to verbal truth because there's
something magical about words there
really is something magical about them
and the way you use words determines the
course of your life and maybe more than
that maybe the course of everyone's life
so I want to explain to you how that can
be true and what it means so you know
that should be relatively entertaining
and hopefully what else I can tell you
is I'm going to throw out some key
propositions there's probably about
seven or eight of them and what I'm
hoping is that you'll be able to use
those propositions as keys that will
help you unlock things that you wouldn't
otherwise be able to consciously
understand and I gave you some example
of that with this little story you know
because that little story happens to be
an extraordinarily deep little story and
it's you know it's it's it's so old that
story like I think that story stems from
when we were still in trees really and
that our when our prime enemies were
snakes because it does appear according
to Lynn Isbell anyways who's a
anthropologist in California that our
primary predators 60 million years ago
when we were basically inhabiting trees
were predatory snakes and that we
co-evolved with and so they're like
human being versus snake motif is not
only the oldest story we know from a
consciously articulated perspective but
it might be the literal story of our
species as a biological entity so you
know that and I'm telling you that
because it gives you some idea about how
deep these stories can go they can go
right to the brilli to the bottom of
things and if you know some of these key
propositions when you see archetypal
stories portrayed in front of you it and
that happens all the time like when all
the superhero movies that have come out
lady or later lately there's you know
hordes of them they're tremendously
expensive to make a hundreds of millions
of dollars those things it's like
they're all predicated in archetypal
themes you know I think it's of great
interest to know the most expensive
artifacts that human beings produce or
at least among the most of expensive
artifacts that we produce are
sigh slee movies that are
computer-generated to tell archetypal
stories you know and that's also the the
technological process that in large part
is driving computer innovation because
the most demand that's being placed on
things like computer chips is actually
you know recreating reality cgi reality
because it's the most complicated thing
to do it's like what the hell why are we
doing that what's up with that why would
you spend 300 million dollars making
Iron Man you know you there's a profit
motive there obviously but everybody
will go see it it's like what's up with
you people you know you'll see some
dingbat in a metal suit fly around in
the air you know that's not true it's
like what are you doing at those movies
you think well I'm entertaining myself
it's like yeah yeah right except why is
it entertaining and why is it
entertaining to all of you and why is it
entertaining to everyone you know
there's a reason for that
so partly what we're going to find out
too is what it is about stories that
attract our interest and why it is why
that is and it's not it's not merely
entertainment it's like the most potent
form of learning that we have so well
anyway so that's the goal and during
this as well you know I hope that you
can articulate yourselves further and
also come to some deeper understanding
about the absolute essential nature of
proper language use in in spoken
language and in written language because
you bet you basically think and speak
and write yourself into existence and
one of the things that means is you
should be very very careful with what
you say because you are literally
bringing realms of reality into being
through speaking and you want to make
bloody sure that the realms of reality
that you're participating and bringing
into being are the ones that you would
actually like yourself and those you
love to inhabit so you know it's a well
I don't have much more to say about the
course than that so what I'll do now is
see if you have any questions so yes
right well yeah you know okay so the
question is why is the Dragon portrayed
as bad it's like well first of all we
might notice that culture cross
culturally that's not necessarily the
case right so the dragon in the West
tends to be something to conquer and and
something that hoards virgins
strangely enough and it's something to
be conquered and the treasure to be
taken but in the East particularly among
the Chinese the dragon is something
that's positive and what I would say is
when we'll study this when we get into
the symbolism that's associated with
with reptiles fundamentally with
predatory reptiles you see that the
dragon is actually a tremendously
ambivalent representation because it
represents it really represents the
unknown or even more precisely it
represents the element of the unknown
that you don't even know exists you know
because sometimes something unexpected
could happen to you but you you can
understand it when it happens but
sometimes something unexpected happens
to you and it's so unexpected that you
can't even conceptualize it I would say
when when the twin towers fell in New
York that was an event like that it's
really domain of your understanding and
then there's a there's an ambivalence
about that because you don't know the
nature of the event precisely so that
the predatory reptile especially the
treasure garden predatory reptile stands
for the potential that exists in the
unknown and that potential can be
positive and negative right because it's
the source of all all new things but
it's also the source of that which will
destroy you and so it's a very
paradoxical entity now one more thing so
so the story implies that there's an
optimal size of dragon and I would say
while your nervous systems are actually
tuned to detect the optimal size of
dragons we'll talk about this in great
detail as we
through the biology of anxiety and
disgust as it turns out which is
something I've learned more about
recently you know how you can sometimes
if you're engaged in a task let's say a
cognitive task you can find it
overwhelming its write something or have
a very difficult time understanding and
maybe you even wonder if you're up to it
okay so you might say well your nervous
system is indicating to you that that's
a threat and then other times you'll be
dealing say with the cognitive task
that's beneath your abilities and so
it's easy and you get bored so then
you'll be dealing with a cognitive task
that it's like Goldilocks and the three
bears right the temperature is just
right and what happens is that you have
to grapple with the task and it pushes
you forward in your development but it
also really engages you
so you're tied right into it it's really
easy to remember and understand it you
make progress and it's difficult and
energy demanding but you're completely
captivated by the process that's the
right size dragon and that's what your
nervous system is telling you it's
saying look this this amount of novel
information in this domain is precisely
the amount that that you can incorporate
well optimally transforming the
knowledge structures that you already
have without exceeding your capacity and
what that does the way your nervous
system signals that to you is you get
interested in it you know and because
you know you might ask yourself like why
do you get interested in things and
you're bored by some things and some
things are overwhelming it's like you
don't have any choice about that it's
not a decision you make right it's
something you discover as you act in the
world and so dragons of optimal size are
engaging and they push your development
but if they get too big then they're too
much potential I see an analogy between
the story with the baby in the krebons
of thunder going hitting everywhere it
could good it could be that like the
thing about the thing about that
particular symbol is that it describes
the unknown outside of the
conceptualization it's pure potential
now you know here's something to think
about in relationship to that I did a
little TED talk on potential which if
you're interested in this sort of thing
you might want to look look at because I
got it right in that talk I thought but
you know you there are different ways of
thinking about what the world's made out
of and you know we think that it's made
out of matter that's the basic dogma say
of the materialist realm and I would say
look it's really useful to treat the
world as if it's made out of matter and
look at all the things that treating in
that way has allowed us to do but that
doesn't mean it's the final statement
about the nature of reality and whatever
matter is is pretty damn strange when
you get to the bottom of it we don't
understand it at all and we don't
understand its relationship to
consciousness but putting that aside we
also act as if things other than matter
are real so for example we act as if
potential is real and that's a very
strange thing you know because potential
by its very nature is not really defined
because otherwise it would be potential
right it would be actuality but you know
all of you understand your parents when
they say well you know you should live
up to your potential
or there's potential there and I would
say actually most of the time when we're
dealing with the world what we're
dealing with is not the material world
per se what we're dealing with is
potential it's like what we're dealing
with what this could be and we're trying
to realize the potential and so another
thing that you could think about think
about with regards to the symbol of the
Dragon in particular it's the predator
the predatory reptile more basically is
that it's a it's a representation of
potential and so and I think the reason
that it takes reptilian form and we're
going to talk about this in great detail
is I think that what happened as we
evolved is that the systems that we
originally evolved to detect predators
constitute underwent a cognitive
revolution
that transformed the world into abstract
representations around us that initial
predatory detection system was
elaborated up into the system that we
use to detect the unknown as such but
you know because it's evolution the
fundamental elements that evolved over
the course of evolution remained intact
we're using the same systems and that
system has a language and so the
language is something like well the
unexpected event is sort of like the
snake in the grass which is perfectly
reasonable you can think about it as a
metaphor it's I think it's deeper than a
metaphor but you can think about it as a
metaphor and I would say well there are
optimal size we have optimal sized
adversaries and I don't think you can
live without an optimal sized adversary
which is also an interesting it's a very
interesting idea because you know one of
the things that people always ask this
is a very metaphysical discussion is you
know why there has to be evil and horror
in the world it's like well it's not
clear to me that the world could be
constituted in the manner that its
constituted in any acceptable way if
there were no adversaries it's like well
maybe the snake in the garden is
necessary you know maybe that
imperfection and also that that
adversary is necessary it's the thing
that spurs on development it it what
would there be without an adversary
maybe nothing you know because you like
to have I can give you an example it's a
funny example there's this little animal
whose name I cannot remember
unfortunately but it lives in the ocean
and in its larval stage it has a brain
swims around it's a little tiny thing it
swims around you know like the little
plankton and so on and then at some
point during its development its fastens
itself onto a rock and it grows into
something that sort of looks like a
plant you know but it's stable it never
moves again so as it develops into this
stable rock clinging entity it basically
digests its own brain and then it
doesn't need one after that and the
reason it doesn't need one is well there
isn't really anything for it to do it
just sits there filters water it takes
like a sponge sort of it takes the the
nutrients of the water in the brain is
just like it's extra energy using tissue
and so it doesn't need the brain anymore
so you know it's like you don't need to
think if you haven't got an adversary so
so then you think well are there optimal
sized adversaries and part of the little
motif of that story is if you pay
careful attention to things as they
change maybe you can keep the damn
adversaries optimized and I think that
actually it may not be true but it's
possible that it's true and that's
something you know that's something if
you really pay because the question
might be and this is something that I
thought about when I was developing all
these are there's a little kind of looks
like okay well there's obviously some
things about existence that aren't
exactly the way you might lay them out
if you had the choice you know like the
fact that people are fundamentally
vulnerable and that you're imperfect in
50 different ways and that life is full
of suffering and everybody dies and you
know all these things that are
existential nightmares it's like okay
fine it's easy to judge that as
unacceptable and maybe even worse than
unacceptable intolerable Ani you know
deserving of obliteration you can even
go that far and people do go that far
but there's another question that that
question begs which is yeah maybe but
maybe if you brought all of your
resources to bear on the problem without
holding back all of them then that would
be okay then you could master it and
that's possible you know so you won't
the thing is you'll never know unless
you try it that's the thing because it's
it's actually a claim that requires an
existential proof you can't listen to
someone tell you that and even if it's
true for them that doesn't necessarily
mean it would be true for you the only
way you can test a proposition like that
is existential you have to act it out
but as I mentioned earlier I see very
very few truly optimistic ideas in
profound thought most profound ideas are
pretty damn pessimistic but this is one
I think that's an exception to that
which is it is possible that you're
constituted so
you have enough resources to deal with
reality as its actually as it actually
lays itself up and one of the ways and
people have been thinking about this for
a very long time too is that the most
effective one of the most effective
weapons you have in that engagement is
the capacity to pay attention and paying
attention and it's another thing I've
learned over the years and that's been
extraordinarily useful to me
we kind of conflate rational thinking
with attention and sort of make
attention like the ugly stepsister of
rationality in some sense because we
never really consider it as a separate
entity because we are basically
rationalist and we believe that we can
deal with the world in rational ways I
don't think that's really true because I
think the world has in it at its core
it's existentially irrational there's
too much of the observe exert an
arbitrary but it is perfectly reasonable
to draw a clear distinction between
paying attention and thinking and you
know Western culture is elevated
thinking in some sense to the to the
position of the highest deity but I
think we've got that wrong I think
attention is much more powerful than
thinking and that attention that
thinking should be the handmaid of
attention because if you pay attention
you can pay attention to the things you
don't know and you can become incredibly
powerful if you pay attention to the
things you don't know because you keep
learning and learning and learning and
learning and you know there was a New
Testament injunction that goes along the
lines of you know it's necessary to love
your enemy and I actually think that
that's that's a an existential hint you
know if you listen to people conversatio
logically minded you have a socialist on
one side and the conservative on the
other all they do is trade platitudes
there's no discussion and the goal of
the discussion is to humiliate the other
person and to prove that you're a priori
stance is correct and that that person
is incapable of conceptualizing the
world property it's like
one of the most interesting things about
running into people who think
differently than you if you pay
attention instead of thinking is they
will tell you the weirdest bloody things
you know the things you never possibly
have thought of and you know it doesn't
mean that you have to all over and agree
with them immediately but what the hell
difference does it make if they don't
think the same way you will you do maybe
though maybe out of ten statements
they'll offer you one then you wouldn't
have conceptualized and that's the
difference between paying attention and
thinking and like people love to be paid
attention to you know it's it's the
currents of currency it's human currency
is attention and attention is an
unbelievably powerful tool you know one
of the things we'll find out is that the
ancient Egyptians actually
conceptualized attention as a god and
the god they conceptualized attention as
was Horus and you all know of course
because you've all seen representations
of course the famous Egyptian I a single
eye that's a representation of Horus and
the Egyptians figured out like the
Mesopotamians have before them that the
highest human deity which is like the
most powerful set of human attributes is
to be associated with one with language
use the Mesopotamians really nailed that
but but even more importantly with the
capacity to pay attention and watch and
it's sort of suspension of judgment it's
like you don't have to be right or wrong
in the situation all you have to do is
pay attention and listen and watch and
then potentially a solution will emerge
out of that and look how our brain is
visual cortex approximately you know so
paying attention were incredible visual
animals paying attention really matters
it's harnessing that's visual attention
in particular but that's the harnessing
of our most fundamental cognitive
capacities so
anyways you know if you pay attention to
things you can see what interests you
and that's also an empirical search in
some sense which is quite interesting
this is part of why I got interested in
psychodynamic ideas it's like there are
things that rule the way that you govern
yourself that you have no control over
you can only discover them and one of
them is what interests you so you can't
really force it if you're not interested
in some things like well good luck
trying to make yourself interested
sometimes you can do it to some degree
but more particularly what seems to
happen is that your interest highlights
things for you and then you follow that
around like you're following up you know
a search beam or something like that and
to me that indicates the action of very
very deep underlying psycho biological
systems that in some sense are directing
your consciousness you know if you pay
attention to that process you can also
learn a tremendous amount from that like
what you're actually like what are you
interested in where is your being trying
to manifest itself that's another way of
thinking about it so those are all
things that we're going to try to figure
out because I would also say that if
you're capable of allowing your true
being to manifest itself so that would
be your potential that's also the best
source you have of the kind of weaponry
that you need to defend yourself against
the inequalities and tragedies and
horrors of life because you can you can
reveal yourself in a sense by pursuing
what's lumen ated for you and I can't
tell you whether or not that's true but
it's a powerful idea and it's a very old
idea and I think there's plenty of
evidence that at least it is a you say
it's plausible
yes it's place it's more than that it's
but plausible will do because I can't
think of a better word into model fits
it's it's it's a hypothesis that has
enough potential that it went you worth
testing and I would like you to test
that sort of thing like one of the
things that I really encourage students
in this class to do and you can start
doing this right ways pay attention to
what you hear yourself say just watch
pull yourself into to detach yourself
from your ideas and thoughts and watch
you say and at the same time that you
watch what you say watch how you feel
when you say what you say and what I'd
like you to try to detect is you'll
notice if you start noticing that some
of the things that you say make you feel
strong and together and United and other
things that you say make you feel
disunited and weak and then I would say
quit saying the ones that make you feel
disunited in weak because they're false
and what you're picking up by the loss
of strength associated with that
utterance is the fact that you're
there's something rotten in the state of
Denmark with regards to that use of
language it's manipulative you're trying
to appear smarter than you are you're
trying to prove a point you're trying to
avoid something like there's some game
you're playing that's other than merely
stating what you see to be true at that
moment and like that's a different way
to live you know because you can you can
calculate and you can plan and planning
is useful I have nothing against that
but you could manipulate reality so that
it manifests what you want or you can
decide that what you're going to do is
pay attention and to call things as you
see them and to see what happens if you
do that and they're like that's a real
risk right because you don't know where
that's going to take you so that's an
act of faith in the character guardian
sense it's like if you have faith in the
truth what that means is that you will
say the truth and that's a hard thing to
do you know it doesn't mean that you can
say whatever you want whenever you want
regardless of the effect on other people
or that you can use the truth as a
baseball bat which you can certainly do
it's it's it's a sophisticated it's it
requires a tremendous amount of
sophisticated it requires a tremendous
amount of sophistication but you know
one thing you might think about is well
if you're if you are attempting to make
yourself a mouthpiece of the truth you
have reality on your side and then you
might say well could you possibly have
anything more powerful on your side
reality and so it might not be a reality
you want or the thing that you wish for
but you might think well you know if you
if you called things as you saw them and
you were very careful about that maybe
that would lead you through life
properly it's a very different way of
thinking and it is tied with this idea
that there's something fundamental about
the truth so I would say to start this
if you want just pay attention to what
you say you know and would like your
detached from it so don't identify too
much with what you're saying because
that's another thing that people do they
identify with what they think it's like
what makes you think that you're
thinking like one of the things you said
which I really loved that blew me just
it just flattened me when I first read
it he said people do not have ideas
ideas have people and so you know I
listened ideologue stalk all the time
it's like that's not them talking and
some dead and dead spirit of the past
that's you know voicing its opinion
through them and you can tell when
you're talking to someone like that
because you can predict everything
they're going to say so in what sense is
that them talking it isn't them talking
at all it's some collective it's a
collective voice that that that has
appropriated them and convinced them
that it's actually part of them it's
like no that's a devil that's what that
is
so so just watch you can try this
experiment all on your own try it for a
month detach yourself from what you say
and think and notice when you say
something if it makes you feel more
grounded and powerful or weaker and stop
saying things that make you weak so you
know that's that's sort of like
existential test number one so well it
must be just about 4 X 4 o 3 so then
I'll see you all next Wednesday take a
look at the website and I will say start
those exercises or
check them out okay